-SCHOOL TRIP 5:00 A.M. -You have a change of clothes?
-（校外教学当天 早上5点） -换洗衣物带了吗？
Socks?
袜子带了吗？
Toothbrush? Wallet?
牙刷呢？钱包呢？
MISSION 68 "IT'S JUST THE SCHOOL FIELD TRIP."
（任务68 校外教学）
Alright, have a good time!
很好 那就好好去玩吧！
NOD!
（点头！）
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind…
不过需要注意的是…
Hey! Komi!
在这边！古见同学！
Over here!
在这里！
They only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
-SHIN-YOKOHAMA STATION -Good morning, Komi.
-（新横滨站） -早安 古见同学
Morning!
早安！
RESTLESS
（紧张不安）
It's so exciting.
既兴奋又期待对吧？
Let's go!
那我们走吧！
Hey-ho!
大家好啊！
Yay! The whole bullet train to ourselves!
好耶！我们包了整辆新干线！
Asleep?
睡着了？
Class president, go make sure everyone is here.
班长 去看看是不是全员到齐了
Alright.
好的
Okay, first…
那么首先…
I can't believe I'm not with Komi.
真不敢相信 我没和古见同学分在同一组
I'm here against my will.
超无奈的
I feel exactly the same way. I'm stuck with this basic chick.
想说那句话的是我才对 我还偏偏和跟风的一组
-Basic? Who are you talking about? -YAMAI, AGARI, NAKANAKA GROUP
-跟风？你说谁啊？ -（山井、上理、中中同学组）
TENSE ATMOSPHERE
（剑拔弩张）
Agari! Hang in there!
上理同学 加油啊！
-So, Inaka, where are you from? -Huh?!
-话说 井中是哪里人啊？ -什么？
You have a bit of an accent.
感觉有点口音呢
Yeah, your accent is so cute.
没错 就是有点口音才可爱
-No, I, uh… -Here, have one.
-不 我 那个… -来 吃点这个吧
Onemine is here so they'll be alright.
有尾根峰同学在 这一组应该没问题
WARM ATMOSPHERE
（温馨）
Inaka is from the countryside and everyone has sort of figured that out.
其实全班同学都已经 隐约察觉到井中同学是乡下小孩了
-SATO, YADANO, USHIRODA GROUP -Unnngh!
-（左藤、矢田野、牛路田同学组） -可恶！
-Gnnngh! -PLAYING OLD MAID
-（玩抽鬼牌中）
10 GAME LOSING STREAK
（已连输十局）
Next time for sure.
下一局我一定要…
-CHIARAI, SHINOBINO, SONODA GROUP -Where should we go?
-（地洗井、忍野、园田组） -要去哪里逛呢？
I want to eat green tea sweets here!
我想去吃这里的抹茶甜点！
Hey, isn't this cute?
快看 不觉得这个很可爱吗？
-Yeah! It's so cute! -So wholesome.
-是啊 真的好可爱喔！ -你们是女生吗？
Seikimatsu, do you have a girlfriend?
世纪末 你有女朋友吗？
Uh, um, actually…
什么？这个嘛 其实…
-OTAKU, SEIKIMATSU, SAMURAI GROUP -Praythee tell us the details!
-（小宅、世纪末、佐村井同学组） -什么？愿闻其详！
Woo-woo!
好恩爱！
What a bunch of characters! They're wholesome too.
这几个人太有个性了吧！ 而且感觉也像是女生间的聊天内容
-KATAI, TADANO, NARUSE GROUP -RUMBLE
（片居、只野、成濑同学组 隆隆声）
I'm in Tadano's group!
居然能和只野同学同一组！
And w-we'll… sleep in the same room!
而且晚上还能共处一室！
Whee!
天啊！
Oh my, I look so good riding the bullet train.
我的天啊 搭新干线的我也太帅了吧
-Uh… This worries me. -RUMBLE
-好令人不安 -（隆隆声）
Yeah, but…
不 但是…
-This worries me more. -SILENCE
-这边更令人不安 -（寂静）
KATO, KOMI, SASAKI GROUP
（加藤、古见、佐佐木同学组）
SHOKO KOMI
（古见硝子）
AYAMI SASAKI
（佐佐木彩美）
So… awkward.
好尴尬啊
Hey, Kato, Komi.
对了 加藤同学、古见同学
W-Want a snack?
要不要吃点心？
Oh! Thanks.
好！谢谢
NOD
（点头）
Oh, it's alright! Go ahead!
不客气！多吃点！
NEARLY UNTOUCHED
（完全没减少）
T-They could have taken more.
可以再多拿一些呀
I wish they would!
反而拜托你们多拿点嘛！
I lost!
又输了！
So… awkward.
好尴尬啊
We don't stand out in class.
平常在班上也不起眼的我们
There's only one thing we can do on this school trip!
在这个校外教学中 能做的只有一件事！
GLANCE
（偷瞄）
Make sure Komi has the best time ever!
就是让古见同学 最大限度地享受这次的校外教学！
That's our mission!
这就是我们的使命！
Kato and Sasaki developed a sort of solidarity.
加藤和佐佐木产生了奇妙的伙伴意识
Komi developed a strange feeling of alienation.
而古见同学则莫名感受到疏离感
It's Kyoto!
京都到了！
Yay!
好棒！
On day one, we'll all travel together. Don't get separated.
第一天要大家一起行动 可别走散了喔
Do I dare set foot on this land?
我这种人有资格踏上这块土地吗？
She's already getting separated!
马上就有一个人感觉快走散了！
Good morning, everyone!
各位早安！
Today on your school trip, I, Ryoko Tenjoin, will be your gus bide.
今天的校外教学由我 天上院旅有子和各位一同“绿行”…
-She flubbed.
-她结巴了 -结巴了
-That's a flub. -She flubbed?
-结巴了呢 -结巴？
-Flub.
-结巴了
I'm very sorry.
十分抱歉
I'm still very new at this, so I might make a few mistakes.
由于我还是新人 可能会出点差错 还请多多谅解
I'm so embarrassed!
好丢脸！
She was actually quite shaken.
其实心里十分动摇
To your right, you can see--
在各位的右手边可以看到…
-Hey! Ryoko! Ryoko! -Uh, yes?
-我有问题 旅有子！ -怎么了？什么事？
Do you have a boyfriend?
你有男朋友吗？
That's it! Top on the "list of questions bus guides get asked," based on a survey.
“游览车女导游最常被校外教学学生 问的问题排行榜”中的第一名来了！
U-Uh, no?
没有喔
-Oh. -Hm?
-这样啊 -什么？
Alright then, I nominate myself.
那么我来做候选人吧
-Here it is! -CHEEKY
-出现了！ -（轻浮）
"Things Cheeky Students Say on Trips." This was ranked first!
“轻浮的校外教学学生问的 难以回答问题排行榜”第一名！
Wow, so segmented.
分得太细了吧
RYOANJI TEMPLE
（龙安寺）
I'm being led by them!
主导权已经被他们掌握了！
They're even walking in front of me!
而且他们还走在我前面！
You can't let this slide, Ryoko!
这样下去可不行啊 旅有子！
I'm a bus guide!
我可是游览车导游！
Yes, bus guides are really cool!
没错 游览车导游可是非常帅气的！
The power of the 2,500 pages of tourist information I memorized.
我这背了共2500页 旅游指南的记忆的实力
I'll show them!
一定要让他们好好见识！
Attention please.
请看这边
This rock garden at Ryoanji
这个龙安寺的石庭
is a Karesansui dry garden with 15 rocks placed in it.
被称为枯山水 且放置15个石头
Wherever you sit on the veranda, one of the rocks will appear concealed.
不论从这个走廊的何处望去 都会有1颗石头是看不见的
There are many theories,
关于这点 众说纷纭
but adding 7, 5, and 3 to make the perfect number 15
有一种说法是 加总7、5、3会变成完美的数字15
and then removing one
而从中减去1
is a message to look within oneself…
代表着让人重新审视自己所欠缺的…
Hm?
怎么了？
Uh… um…
那个…
They're not listening!
他们根本没在听！
SHE IS PRETTY, BUT…!!
（虽然她长得很美啦！）
No, Ryoko.
不 旅有子
It's not time to panic just yet.
现在慌张失措还太早了
I won't let you keep ignoring me for much longer!
你们能对我的导览 没兴趣也只有现在了！
Never underestimate a bus guide!
可别小看游览车导游！
Here we have Kinkakuji.
接着我们看这座金阁寺
It was made by Ashikaga Yoshimitsu,
是由室町幕府第三任将军
the third shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.
足利义满所建设的
Ashikaga Yoshimitsu is famous for appearing in a certain anime.
说起足利义满 他在某部动画中出现过所以很有名
Which anime would that be?
是哪部动画呢？
Yeah, here we go.
好戏上场！
One of the 108 best bus guide tricks. The quiz!
游览车导游108招之第1招 猜谜！
Well? You can't help but answer, can you?
怎么样啊？ 压抑不住想回答的冲动吧？
Uh. What is it? I don't know.
什么？是什么？不知道
It's a golden building but it fades before my charm.
就连金光闪闪的建筑 在我魅力面前也是黯然失色
What's up with him?
什么？这个同学是怎样？
-Excuse me! -Hm?
-不好意思！ -怎么了？
Could we ask for a photo?
可以拍照吗？
Oh.
这样啊
Go ahead!
请拍！
-Um, no, we want you to… -…take a picture of us.
-不是啦 我们是想请你… -帮我们拍照
-Ah. -Never mind.
-啊 -当我没说好了
Tends to think people want his picture.
以为别人想拍他
What's with these kids?
这些学生到底是怎样？
-Momotaro! -No…
-《桃太郎》！ -答错了
The answer is Ikkyu-san.
顺带一提 答案是《一休和尚》
-NISHI HONGWANJI -I-I've got to pull myself together.
-（西本愿寺） -重振精神吧
Hongwanji is the main temple of the Jodo Shinshu sect.
这座本愿寺是净土真宗 本愿寺派的总本山
The temple was built in the Kamakura period by Shinran Shonin.
始于镰仓时代亲鸾圣人所建立的寺堂
Inside, the national treasure building, Hiunkaku, along with Kinkaku and Ginkaku
而其中的国宝建筑物 飞云阁 与金阁、银阁并列
is one of Kyoto's three famous "kaku" buildings.
为京都三大名阁…
Huh.
是喔
They're not interested!
他们根本不感兴趣！
DAZED
（发呆）
Ugh, a tough crowd!
天啊 好难对付！
-Are you really from a prep school? -Look, Komi!
-话说你们真的是读升学高中吗？ -快看 古见同学！
-They were selling these! -SHINSENGUMI DRESS-UP SET
-有卖这种衣服耶！ -（成为新选组套装）
She already bought a wooden sword!
她居然这么快就买了木刀！
What a freak!
太可怕了！
Oh, that's right!
对了！
Here at Nishi Hongwanji, the drum tower
西本愿寺的太鼓楼
was once used as the Shinsengumi police headquarters.
曾有段时期被当作新选组的驻地使用
From Shimabara Omon to Sumiya Mibudera,
想必当时从岛原大门到角屋壬生寺
many soldiers wore that same jacket as they patrolled the area.
都曾有许多队士 穿着羽织外衣通行往来吧
Well? Kids your age love Shinsengumi, don't they?
如何？你们这年纪的小孩 应该都喜欢新选组对吧？
C'mon, take an interest!
来吧！表现得感兴趣一些！
So we meet again, Kondo.
许久不见了 近藤先生
What is this act? Who does that?
这是什么小剧场？有必要吗？
-PRIEST -Yay!
-（大僧正） -耶！
FLASH
（拍照）
That girl is always eating something.
这位同学老是在吃东西呢
-34, 35… -SHIMOGAMO SHRINE
-34、35… -（贺茂御祖神社）
We're missing someone! Are they lost?
少一个人！迷路了吗？
Wow!
天啊
Oh!
糟了！
My stomach suddenly…
我的肚子突然有点…
Um.
那个…
Paw…
手…
-Paw? -(WHERE IS THE) POW(DER ROOM?)
-“手”？ -（洗手间在哪里？）
-I'm exhausted. -Are you alright?
-总觉得已经精疲力尽了 -你还好吗？
Oh, everyone.
各位请看
On your left, you'll see the Kyamo River.
在各位左手边的是“牙川”…
-Augh! -KAMO RIVER
-讨厌！ -（鸭川）
It's alright. At any rate, nobody is listening to me anyway.
算了啦 反正根本没人在听我说话
Here,
来这里的…
for some reason the couples who visit sit the same distance apart.
那些情侣们 不知为何 都会以固定间距坐着
That's what it's famous for.
所以以此闻名
They really are the same distance apart!
他们真的隔着固定间距坐着耶！
That's so interesting!
真有趣呢！
Oh, yes. How could I forget?
对了 我怎么忘了呢？
If even one person takes an interest,
只要有任何一个人对我的导览感兴趣
I've achieved my dream of becoming the ideal bus guide!
我不就成为了一直向往的 那个理想中的游览车导游了吗？
In spring and summer, the river terraces make a stunning view.
在春夏之际会露出河床 可以欣赏充满情调的风景
I hope everyone will come back to Kyoto again!
希望各位以后有机会可以再访京都！
"To jump from the Kiyomizu stage," is a famous figure of speech.
有句俗语是 “从清水的舞台一跃而下”
It's 13 meters above ground, as tall as a four-story building.
清水的舞台约13米高 也就等于四层大楼的高度
There's a 90% survival rate, but please don't try it.
存活率有九成 还蛮高的 但请各位还是不要轻易模仿
Woo! From the Kiyomizu stage!
我也要从清水的舞台…
I will jump!
一跃而下！
Hey there, Najimi.
别这样做啦 驯染同学
From the right, they give fortune in health, love, and academics.
据说从右至左分别能带来 健康、恋爱、学问方面的保佑
Yamai!
山井同学！
Hm? Those two aren't here.
奇怪 那两个人不在这里
Did they get lost?
会不会是跟大家走散了？
Oh!
真棒！
Oh, you were here, Komi?!
天啊 原来你在 古见同学！
-LOOKING AT THE ARCHITECTURE? -Uh, yes.
-（你在看木造工法吗？） -对啊
It was made without a single nail.
据说一根钉子也没用到耶
Erecting such a big building on a cliff…
在这悬崖边盖这么大的建筑
Every day thousands of people stand on it and it doesn't fall apart. Amazing!
每天还有几千人站在上面 却不会崩塌 真是太厉害了！
I spoke a little too fast. That was weird, wasn't it?
我刚才语速太快了 有点恶心吧？
Sorry.
抱歉
I'M IN LOVE TOO.
（我也喜欢）
WITH OLD BUILDINGS!
（像这样的古建筑！）
Yes, that's it.
也对 我想也是啦
Get married already.
你们赶快去结婚啦
That's what she thought.
她这么想
-Um… Huh? -RYOKO GAVE A PAW.
（什么？那个… 将手放上去的旅有子）
A traditional inn! A traditional hostess!
旅馆！老板娘！
Our room is huge!
一间超大的客房！
Hang on, are you in our room?
什么？等等 你跟我们住同一间房间？
-Huh? -Don't give me that.
-什么？ -你疑惑什么？
Dinner was so good!
晚餐真好吃！
Each group gets 30 minutes for the bath. Go now!
从第一组开始洗澡 每组30分钟 快去洗吧！
Okay!
好！
Good evening! It's me, Ren Yamai!
大家晚安啊！我是山井恋！
This is it!
终于迎来这一刻了！
The biggest event of the school trip! The bath!
校外教学一大盛事 洗澡！
My goal for today is to touch Komi's boo… her skin.
我今天的目标就是 摸到古见同学的胸…肌肤
We're both girls so it's perfectly normal!
我们都是女生 所以做这种事算是很稀松平常！
That was a great bath!
泡得真舒服！
C'mon, let's go to the bath!
来吧 我们去洗澡吧！
WOMEN'S BATH
（女用浴室）
Okay Komi. Your clothes… take them off.
来吧 古见同学 把衣服脱掉吧
C'mon and show me the breasts I missed at the pool this summer!
快让我看看在夏天的泳池 没能看到的古见同学的胸部！
FIVE MINUTES LATER
（五分钟后）
-FOR YAMAI IT FELT LIKE AN HOUR -Why?
-（对山井同学而言像过了一小时） -为什么？
-EMBARRASSED -Why won't you get undressed, Komi?
-（害羞） -你为什么不脱啊？古见同学
Hey!
嘿！
Hm? You haven't gotten in the bath yet?
什么？你还没去洗澡吗？
Agari hasn't either.
上理同学也是
It's a little embarrassing, isn't it?
要在别人面前露出肌肤
To get naked in front of people.
还是会有点害羞对吧？
In the bath during my junior high trip,
我初中校外教学去洗澡的时候
they called me "Meatballs."
别人叫我“肉丸子”
T-That must've hurt.
那真是让人难受
If you hide yourself with a towel, it'll be okay.
不过用浴巾遮住应该就没问题了吧
Here.
来
Anyway, I'm jealous of you!
我还反倒羡慕你呢
I'm super flat-chested after all.
像我这样根本就是洗衣板
Himiko, you're stacked! You should feel confident.
卑美子那么丰满 可以更有自信一点喔
Himiko, Himiko…
卑美子…
This struck a chord with Agari.
有东西触动了上理同学的心弦
Y-Yes, Onemine!
好的 尾根峰同学！
DROOP
（沉甸甸）
Meatballs.
肉丸子
Those two ruined my view.
那两个人害我什么也没看到
But I realized if I wait here, I'll be able to see her.
但仔细想想 只要待在这里等 应该随时都能尽情看吧
This seat is open.
这里有空位喔
It must be hard to have such long hair.
长头发洗起来真麻烦啊
Komi.
古见同学
Can I touch your boobs?
我可以摸你的胸部吗？
So direct!
（直接了当！）
But wait.
但是先等等
Her eyes were clear.
她的眼神如此清澈
As clear as crystal.
如此地晶莹剔透
Clear as an alpine plateau. Clear as a baby's eyes.
就像是阿尔卑斯的高原 又如同婴儿无邪的眼神
Yes. Ren Yamai had no wicked thoughts.
没错 山井恋没有一丝邪念
Komi's angelic naked skin had washed away Ren Yamai's wicked thoughts.
古见同学圣洁的肌肤 除去了山井恋的所有邪念
Now, she was only thinking of touching Komi's boobs.
现在她只是一心想摸古见同学的胸部
-If that's not pure, then what is? -I WANT TO TOUCH KOMI'S BOOBS.
-若这不是纯真无邪 那什么才是？ -（好想摸古见同学的胸部）
But Komi still turned her down.
但还是被拒绝了
Tadano.
只野
Hm?
怎么了？
I have a riddle for you.
我出个谜题考考你
O-Okay.
好
It has four legs, but cannot walk. I couldn't believe it myself, back then.
有种“面包”不能吃 但那时的我不相信这件事
T-This is…
这里就是…
This is the room where Tadano and I and the others will spend the night!
我和只野同学或其他同学 要共度一夜的房间！
I'm so nervous!
好紧张喔！
-THE CLASS DELINQUENTS -GLOOM
（班上的不良少年 阴沉）
We're stuck with that weird guy in our room.
和奇怪的家伙分到同一间房了
We can't goof off.
完全不能大声喧哗
He's looking at us.
他在看我们
He's staring!
死盯着我们！
We'll be sharing a room. I should say hello.
我们住同一间房间 得先打个招呼才行
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
Evening, fellas.
请多指教
-So we die tonight. -THAT'S HOW IT SOUNDS
-看来我们只能活到今晚 -（听起来像是这样说）
MEN'S BATH
（男用浴室）
They look so down.
别那么沮丧
Look upon my body and rejoice.
欣赏我的身体振作起来吧
They won't rejoice.
振作不起来
Alright then.
好了
Alright!
洗完了！
Whoa!
天啊！
They rejoiced.
他们振作起来了
Oh no, I left my lotion at home.
完了 我忘记带爽肤水了
My skin gets so dry without it.
没有爽肤水的话皮肤会变干燥耶
-Katai. -Hm?
-片居 -什么？
Use this.
用这个吧
Katai.
片居
You've got a great body.
你身材不错嘛
Take it off.
把衣服脱了
L-Like this? Is that alright?
这样就好了吗？
Yes, it's good. Just like that.
没错 很好 非常棒！
-SAY CHEESE! -Tadano, did you get the shot?
-（笑一个！） -只野 你拍到了吗？
Uh, yeah.
嗯 拍到了
It's a work of art!
这就是艺术！
H-Hey.
喂！
Can… we join in?
也可以让我们加入吗？
C'mon.
来吧
We'll make some art with the Kyoto nightscape in the background!
好！让我们以京都的夜景为背景 爆发我们的艺术光彩吧！
Yeah!
好！
-STARTING TO HAVE FUN -More to the left!
-（开始乐在其中） -再左边一点 没错！
The composition is perfect.
这个构图太完美了
It's great! Wonderful!
很好！非常棒！
Your bodies are like sculptures!
像雕像般的身体！
Washboard abs!
像板状巧克力的腹肌！
Wow, this is awesome!
天啊 太棒了！
F-Fabulous!
实在太美妙啦！
The fight for our sleeping spots! We're holding a pillow fight!
争夺床位的丢枕头大战开打！
The rules are simple!
规则十分简单！
The last person standing is the victor!
屹立不摇到最后的人为胜者！
I want to sleep near Komi!
想睡在古见同学的附近！
BOFF
（丢中）
What are you doing, Komi?
你在做什么呢？古见同学
You should jo--
古见同学也来玩…
Are you ready to give in yet, Najimi?
你差不多该放弃了吧？驯染
It looks like we've both reached our limits, Yamai.
看来我们彼此都到极限了呢 山井
This is my final strike!
吃我最后…
Last pitch!
一击！
Is everyone sleeping?
大家都睡了吗？
Good.
很好
Yamai, are you asleep?
山井睡着了吗？
I could never fall asleep that fast.
怎么可能那么快就入睡？
So annoying!
吵死了！
TWITCH
（吓到）
She was wakeful and couldn't sleep.
她觉得精神抖擞 睡不着
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：吴敬美